<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Captain Thorogood his opinion of the point of succession, to a brother of the blade in Scotland</title>
            <author>Thorogood, B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13534724</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13534724</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62468)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 478:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Captain Thorogood his opinion of the point of succession, to a brother of the blade in Scotland</title>
                  <author>Thorogood, B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: B. T. and dated Jan. 3, 1679.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Captain Thorogood His Opinion of the Point of SUCCESSION, To a Brother of the Blade in SCOTLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Jack,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I covet nothing ſo much as to ſee the Exorbitant Power of <hi>France</hi> reduc'd to its ancient bounds; ſo I am ſenſible no Nation upon Earth can ſtop the rapid Courſe of their Victories but Ours, whoſe Valour ſtill fills their hearts with no leſs fear then their late Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have done with ambition: But I confeſs the conſideration of Ourpreſent unhappy differences makes me dread loſing the opportunity of reſcuing enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Christendom</hi> from their Tyrany, and Our own Glory from the ſtains of Infamy, contracted b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he over-long repoſe of our Arms. This fear I look upon to be well-grounded, ſince no leſs a thing is ſaid to be in agitation then a change in the very Fundamentals of our Government, which like a diſtemper that ſeizes the noble Parts, muſt (after the long ſtruglings and conflicts of the contending parties;) extremely weaken. if not abſolutely deſtroy it, as is evident by the no leſs impious then doleful examples of all Ages; And if that ſhould once happen, (which God in his Mercy prevent,) who would be able to reſiſt the mighty Force of <hi>France?</hi> or what could <hi>England</hi> (which alone, if united, is capable to prevent it,) expect but with the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> (and upon harder conditions then any other Nation) be ſwallow'd up in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Monarchy? To prevent which, ſince nothing can more effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute then a firm and laſting Union among Our ſelves, which is morally impoſſible to be attained, if once the ancient and fundamental form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, under which this Nation has (to its Immortal Renown, and its Enemies Terror,) flouriſhed ſo many Generations, be now aboliſed. I thought fit in a Soldierly manner, and <hi>en Cavalier,</hi> to ſhew you that the juſt excluſion of His Royal Highneſs from the Imperial Crown of this Realm, (in caſe the King ſhould die without Iſſue) is abſolutely impoſſible; and this I do on no other account, but becauſe I believe it may do my Country good, whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, as well as Glory, it will be, to have a Prince of Martial Spirit Reign over Us, by whoſe Valour Our almoſt withered <hi>Lawrels</hi> may once more be planted in <hi>French-ground,</hi> moiſten'd and made fat with the Bloud of our implacable Enemies, and nouriſh'd and rear'd up to that Strength and Vigour they formerly enjoyed by the Courage and Conduct of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100041:2"/>
            <p> You know it is the common Theme of the Town-Scriblers, than <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> is a meer Humane Inſtitution, alterable in <hi>Part;</hi> or in the <hi>Whole,</hi> as often as the <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>Governed</hi> ſhall think it neceſſary for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Safety. That the <hi>King</hi> for the time being is the Supreme <hi>Governour,</hi> and the whole Aggregate of People the <hi>Governed.</hi> That theſe being not otherwiſe eaſily to be aſſembled, are ſome perſonally, and the reſt by their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives in Parliament. That whatever Law or Sanction, the King, with the advice and conſent of his People ſo conven'd does Enact, binds the whole Nation; and that conſequently it is in their Power to exclude His <hi>R. H.</hi> the Succeſſion, or, which is the ſame thing, to turn the <hi>Hereditary Monarchy</hi> into an <hi>Elective.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Poſition, (how injurious ſoever to a Succeſſor,) is more dangerous to a Prince Regnant, who if weak, eaſie, or inconſiderate, may, through hope, or fear, be prevail'd upon to yield to his own dethroning, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change his actual Royalty for an Annuity or yearly Penſion; whereas the other loſes only a poſſibility of a Crown, with this further advantage, That <hi>moſt Men will think him worthy of wearing it, becauſe not the want of Courage and Magnanimity, but of Intereſt and Power creates his Misfortune.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever then ſhall be ſaid to ſhew the impracticableneſs of this Poſition here in <hi>England,</hi> is as much intended to ſecure the Poſſeſſion of His moſt Sacred Majeſty, or any other that ſhall lawfully fill the Throne, as the poſſibility which His <hi>R. H.</hi> now has, or any other Heir Apparent may have in after Ages. It is indeed a Royal Cauſe, and as ſuch to be maintain'd by the Swords and Pens of all good Subjects, of which number I profeſs my ſelf to be one, and in evidence of my <hi>Loyalty</hi> ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſince <hi>England</hi> is <hi>de facto</hi> a Hereditary Kingdom, and every King for the time being, with the help of his <hi>Parliaments</hi> entruſted with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it as ſuch; it follows, that as he cannot alien or ſubject it to another Crown or Perſon, becauſe the alienation of a Kingdom is ſo far from being comprehended in the Government of it, by him (to whom firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) and his Heirs, that it is directly repugnant and inconſiſtent with it, ſo he cannot alter the courſe and order of Succeſſion, which is a kind of aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it transfers the Title to one who (without ſuch an Act) would have none; and conſequently any Monarch attempting the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the very Form and Eſſence of ſuch a Government, may be thought rather to fruſtrate in ſome meaſure part of the Truſt repoſed in him, and ſtray from his Duty, then vitiate his Succeſſors Title to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If both Houſes of Parliament ſhould be allowed to have a ſhare in the Government in a co-ordinate manner with the King, then the King and they (having the Supreme Power of Governing a Hereditary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy committed to their Charge, and nothing elſe,) have no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to alter or deſtroy it; becauſe a Power to ſupport and maintain a Government, and change and diſſolve it, is abſolutely inconſiſtent with it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This great truſt was repoſed in them either by <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> if by <hi>God,</hi> then 'tis certain it cannot warrantably be alter'd without his poſſitive command infallibly known as ſuch; If by <hi>Man,</hi> we are under the diſability until his expreſs Will and Pleaſure be made known to us, in a plain, evident and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable way.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100041:2"/>
            <p> God has not yet revealed us his Will or Deſire to change our Government, nor are we to look for ſuch extraordinary Injunctions at this time, when the light of the Goſpel has ſufficiently cleared all the Errors and Doubts that might hinder our Duty; And it is an act of equal Folly and Impiety to attempt an Innovation upon the ſuppoſition of being able to know certainly and unqueſtionably the Will of <hi>Man,</hi> ſince that knowledge will (to any that ſeriouſly conſiders the Conſtitution of this Kingdom) appear abſolutely impoſſible. For if by <hi>Man</hi> we underſtand (as we muſt) the whole Complex of the People, or the <hi>Governed,</hi> we cannot poſſibly be ſatisfied of their being after a full and mature deliberation, deſirous of a Change, becauſe we have, or at leaſt will uſe no other way of knowing their minds, but by their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in Parliament; and theſe whom we commonly call <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> are either not ſo at all; or if they be, do not derive their Power from a third part of the Nation, and conſequently cannot impart a knowledge to us, which they themſelves never had, or execute an Authority which was never given 'em, according to the old Maxim, <hi>nemo dat quod non habet;</hi> The reaſon why they may be thought to be no Repreſentatives at all, is, becauſe if the ultimate and laſt reſult of Power, ſuch as is doubtleſs the diſpoſing of the Crown, be in the King and Parliament only, it cannot rationally be ſaid, That the Parliament is the People which is always to be the party Governed; it being as impoſſible that they ſhould at one and the ſame time, and in the ſame reſpect, be both <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Governed,</hi> as it is for me to be <hi>Master</hi> and <hi>Servant,</hi> in regard to my ſelf ſingly and alone. But to wave this, which may poſſibly be looked upon as a ſubtilty or ſtrained Notion; I ſay that the Parliament as now uſually Elected, is not at all the Repreſentative of the People; I mean ſo as to have ſuch an actual or virtual Deputation or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from every individual perſon, as may enable them to exerciſe all the Acts relating to Government, as arbitrarily, and without controll; as if all the People were perſonally preſent, and conſenting to ſuch Acts. For none have Votes in Elections, but <hi>Free-holders</hi> of at leaſt forty Shillings a Year, and <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> and conſequently all <hi>Leſſees</hi> for Years, <hi>Grantees</hi> of <hi>Annuities</hi> for Years: <hi>Men</hi> that live upon the Intereſt, and Product of their Money: The greateſt part of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> all <hi>Soldiers,</hi> and <hi>Seamen</hi> in general, moſt of the young <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> who beſides their poſſibilities of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders, ſeldom have any thing for their maintenance but their Parents allowances; And in fine, the whole number of <hi>Labourers, Servants, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen,</hi> not reſiding in, or at leaſt free of Cities and Boroughs, are totally excluded, and conſequently no more repreſented by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then the Attorney you authorized to appear for you this Term in a Suit at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> is warranted by the Authority you gave him, to appear likewiſe for me without my knowledge or privity; And what can be more unequal, not to ſay unjuſt, then that a numerous and upon due computation the far greateſt part of the Nation, that are Paſſengers in the great Ship of the Commonwealth, as well as the reſt, ſhould be debarred their right of chooſing a <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Pilot,</hi> to whoſe Skill and Care they commit their common ſafety? Have they not their <hi>Liberty,</hi> their <hi>Property,</hi> their <hi>Religion;</hi> and in a word, the preſent enjoyments of this, and in ſome meaſure the hopes of a future <hi>Life</hi> to be ſecured or hazarded by the good or ill Conduct of their <hi>Governour?</hi> And muſt this, all this be left to the Arbitrary Power and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of ſuch, as by chance, perhaps more then merit, have acquired the Poſſeſſion of ſome Land, or are free of Boroughs and Cities? If a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of forty Shillings <hi>per annum,</hi> intitles one to as a great a ſhare of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100041:3"/> Legiſlative Power, as that of five thouſand Pound does another, what ſhew of Reaſon can there be, why one whoſe Goods and Chattels amount to ten times the value of ſuch a Free-hold, and has peradventure a Stock of Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Honeſty and Wiſdom as many degrees beyond him, ſhould not be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd in the Government?</p>
            <p>But allowing <hi>Free-holders, Citizens</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> ſome Myſterious and Sacred <hi>Right,</hi> excluſively of all others, of delegating the Repreſentatives, and irrevocable Attorneys of the whole Kingdom; yet ſurely there ſhould be ſuch a proportion and equality between them, as would render this mighty Power veſted in them, agreeable to Right Reaſon, and the very nature of Government; But we ſee no ſuch thing for the meaneſt Borough; For <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Old Sarum</hi> deputes as many men to ſerve in Parliament, as the greateſt County in <hi>England,</hi> with equal Authority, not only of conſulting and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but likewiſe of giving their determinative and deciſive Voices in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and things whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornwal</hi> which is the two and fiftieth part of the Kingdom, makes above an eleventh part of the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> and yet <hi>London, Southwark.</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which in the Power of Men and Riches, is judged to be a ſixth of the whole Nation, is in the Repreſentative but the ſixty fourth part. And this Soleciſm alone in the very conſtitution of the Government will make it for ever impoſſible to have the People Repreſented in any juſt and rational manner; unleſs perhaps ſuch courſe might be taken, as is practiced in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where each Province ſends as many Deputies as it pleaſes, with power of propoſing and debating, but not of reſolving by the Votes of the Perſons, but of the Provinces.</p>
            <p>It may be here objected that our preſent Conſtitution has appointed no other way for chooſing Repreſentatives; and that therefore we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce: To this I Anſwer, that it may very well fall our, that nothing may be a clearer and greater hinderance to our having a true and evident know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Peoples Deſires and Inclinations by their Repreſentatives, then our very Laws; For <hi>example,</hi> at preſent the <hi>Oaths of Allegiance, Supremacy,</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> are to be taken by all the Members of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; But if in this, or any after-age, almoſt the whole, or the far greater part of the Nation, ſhould become true <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who abhor our <hi>Royal</hi> as much as the <hi>Papal Supremacy,</hi> or <hi>Quakers</hi> that indeed ſcruple all <hi>Oaths,</hi> or <hi>Papiſts</hi> that cannot well be ſuppos'd willing to renounce the whole ſubſtance of their Religion; could the few, (who by taking ſuch <hi>Oaths,</hi> would then be rendred capable of ſitting in Parliament,) be properly accounted the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives</hi> of a Nation, that could not otherwiſe look upon them, then as men wicked, irreligious, and perjured, and conſequently more forward to heighten then heal their Miſeries; To which end no man can be rationally ſuppoſed to depute another? No ſure, and therefore when Laws which are made for the People, (and not the People for the Laws) do croſs and thwart the Right and Intereſt of the major part of the Society, they then not being able to effect what they were deſigned for, become uſeleſs, and die.</p>
            <p>A further Objection will be, that the conſtant opinion of all Ages has put it beyond doubt, that the Parliament is the Repreſentative of the People; and that all the Acts they paſs, do virtually include the conſent and agreement of every individual perſon in the Kingdom: To this I would very readily
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100041:3"/> agree, provided it would be allowed me on the otherhand, (as appears b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all our Law Books,) that <hi>Monarchy</hi> is <hi>Jure naturae,</hi> and unalterable without apparent Violence by any Humane Power whatſoever; But if the arrogance or malice of ſome will carry them ſo far as to trample upon all the Poſitive and Fundamental Laws of the Land, and publiſh daily in Print, to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt hazard of the State, that all Forms or kinds of Government, are changable at the Will and Pleaſure of the People, into that <hi>Species</hi> which ſhall by them be thought the moſt agreeable, to their Natures and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I hope it will not be looked upon as a Crime in me, if following the way they chalked out for me, and waving the common received opinion, I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpeculatively pry, into the very Conſtitution and Frame of Parliaments, thereby to ſhew the impoſſibility of altering the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> But to clear all Objections as far as poſſible, I ſay, That the ſuppoſition, of the Parliaments repreſenting the People, is a fiction of Law, well deviſed by the Wiſdom of our Anceſtors, for quieting and appeaſing the minds of all particular men, who could not have a ſtronger Motive of Submiſſion, or of not believing themſelves injured then their being accounted parties and privy to all Acts of Parliament; But this fiction of Law cannot reach the Actual Legiſlators, as ſuch, ſince they cannot be ſuppoſed to wrong themſelves, though they might thoſe by whom commiſſioned. The Parliament, then when it alters or repeals Laws, lops off the exuberancies and excreſcencies, which by the deſign or heedleſneſs of the Managers, grow up in the Government, curbs the Pride, A varice and encroachments of great Perſons bounds and limits reciprocally the Princes Prerogative and Subjects Liberty; and in fine lends its healing hand towards the removing any thing that is dangerous or noxious to the Body Politick as firſt conſtituted, then, I ſay, it may well enough for its greater Strength and Authority, be allowed the Repreſentative of the whole Body of the People: But if inſtead of applying fit remedies for its preſervation and continuance, they ſhould go about to annihilate or diſſolve it, which muſt inevitably be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with violent concuſſions and univerſal calamities, it cannot, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be accounted their Repreſentative; becauſe the conſequence of ſuch an Act muſt immediately influence every individual Member of the Society; and 'tis but reaſon that the common concernment of the ruine or happineſs of all; ſhould be left, not by fiction of Law, but in reality, to be weighed by their own Judgment: For if (as ſome would have it) the Power of Dominion was originally in the People, and by them transferred on <hi>one, few</hi> or <hi>many</hi> of themſelves, 'tis evident that as every one was actually aiding by his choice and agreement in erecting ſuch a Dominion, ſo it's neceſſary he ſhould by the ſame means concur to its change and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be ſaid that our Government was firſt eſtabliſhed not by the Votes of Individuals, but by Repreſentatives in the Nature of Parliaments, as now conſtituted; I Anſwer, that it could not be, becauſe of the inequality of the choice, which is certain was not in the beginning; (for until the <hi>8th.</hi> year of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> as is plain by the Statute then made, the Electors of Knights of the Shire were not under a neceſſity of having forty Shillings <hi>per annum</hi> to expend) or if it was, let our Adverſaries prove when and where it firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; if they cannot, but confidently and poſitively affirm it was ſo, and we as confidently and poſitively deny it, then 'tis evident; we being in poſſeſſion, that the advantage will be of our ſide, for <hi>in equali jure melior eſt conditio poſſidentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Having thus far endeavour'd to prove that the Parliament is not the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100041:4"/> Repreſentative of the People. I further ſay, That allowing them to be ſo, yet 'tis certain they aſſemble not of themſelves, but by the King's Writ, which ſets forth the occaſion of their being call'd, <hi>viz.</hi> to adviſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, <hi>&amp;c. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arduis &amp; urgentibus negotiis Regni,</hi> of the great and preſſing Affairs of the Kingdom; Now the Kingdom being Hereditary at the time of iſſuing forth the Writ, and they ſummoned to appear and give their advice concerning the good Eſtate and Defence of it as ſuch, 'tis plain they cannot change, alter or deſtroy it, no more then a Phyſician ſent for, to remove the Pains and Oppreſſions of Sickneſs, can lawfully ſtab or poyſon his Patient, who through rage or folly may yield his aſſent to his own deſtruction. 'Tis ridiculous and fooliſh to think that even the very Country would not with high Indignation reſent ſuch an attempt, ſince they know full well that the Election of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to conſtitute the Body Politick of a Parliament, was never intended to deſtroy the Head and moſt eſſential part of it, I mean the Hereditary King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which abſtractedly from this or that man, who may give an ill Preſident, and therefore is not intruſted with an abſolute diſpoſal of it, is the very Life and Soul of the Government, and without which it muſt infallibly crumble into pieces.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We all know that a Body Politick, which is the Work and Creature of Man, has many reſemblances with the Body Natural, which is the Creature of God; for as this aims always at its eaſe, happineſs and long preceptions of the pleaſures of this Life, and conſequently dreads and abhors Death or Diſſolution which puts an end to all, ſo the other is conſtant and unwearied in the purſuit of the like ends to that degree, that by its very conſtitution and eſſential form we attribute to it a kind of Immortality, whence comes the known Maxim received into our Laws, <hi>That the King never dies,</hi> that is, that Kingſhip, not the Perſons to whom it is inherent or annexed for this, or that time, is beyond the reach of Fate and Time that puts and end to all things. This then being ſo, we cannot rationally conclude that our preſent Sovereign has Will or Power to deſtroy himſelf, that is, Hereditary Kingſhip, which made him what he is, and is as eſſential to the Politick Capacity he is in, as Supreme Governour, as the rational Soul is to his natural Capacity, as man. To ſay or judge otherwiſe, would be no leſs, then to put him to break all the ſacred ties of Love which bind him ſo ſtrongly to himſelf, and ſuppoſe him capable to be in ſome meaſure his own Executioner, and a <hi>Felo de ſe</hi> of Monarchy, then which there can be no greater Indignity offered to the Majeſty of a Prince whom we all know to be Juſt, Merciful and Generous to others; and who therefore muſt ſo much the more ſignally practice thoſe Vertues towards him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by how much ſelf-reſpect exceeds that due to another.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly, 'Tis evident by ſeveral Statutes, that all Knights' of the Shires, and their Electors are to be Inhabitants and Reſidents in the reſpective Counties the day of the Writ, and that likewiſe the Citizens and Burgeſſes are to be men reſident, dwelling and free in the Cities and Boroughs for which they are to be choſen; And right reaſon teaches us that none ought by ſiniſter and unjuſt means to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into Authority, if therefore any one be previouſly diſabled ahd uncapable to exerciſe Power by a poſitive Law, or openly by deceits, calumnies or corruption thruſt himſelf into the Seat of Juſtice, 'tis certain all his Proceedings and Sanctions do carry a nullity and inſufficiency in themſelves, and affect none, beſides the Maker, who by endeavouring to exerciſe a Legiſlative Power againſt Law and Reaſon, makes his violation of them ſo much the more manifeſt. This often happens in chooſing of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-men
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100041:4"/> in our days, when thoſe that live in the <hi>North</hi> are choſen for the <hi>South,</hi> and men that never ſaw the Cities or Boroughs before the time of Election made their Repreſentatives, with this further addition of diſability, that they gain Votes by Bribes, Treats, and many unlawful Artifices, as by loading their Competitors with the moſt odious calumny of being Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, Penſioners, Papiſts Atheiſts, and what not? though they know them to have more love for their Country and their Religion then themſelves. I know nothing that can more effectually fruſtrate the Decrees and Reſolves of Law-makers then this, and therefore leave it to impartial and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent men to judge whether ſuch a practice, if it ſhould intervene, would not exclude any Society of Men from excluding another from his Right.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter then the preſent Monarchy is ſo founded, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King nor the Parliament can poſſibly alter the true and eſſential form of it; and conſequently his <hi>R. H.</hi> cannot be barr'd his Right of Reigning over us, if he ſurvive his Brother, whoſe Life he values beyond the Crowns and Kingdoms he can leave him, whom God long preſerve in Peace and Plenty, and the unfeigned affection of his People.</p>
            <p>As for the Examples which are alledged to evince the contrary, and urged ſo confidently by the Gentleman that is the Author of the <hi>Word without Doors</hi> they do not at all ſcare me, for the Queſtion is not whether <hi>de facto,</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without violation of Juſtice and the Principles of right Reaſon, our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy may be changed? For no man ever doubted but Power, Rebellion and Faction with the concurrence of timorous and eaſie Princes did often turn things into Tragical Confuſions, and unhinge the whole frame of <hi>Governments,</hi> but far be it from us to ground the lawfulneſs of our Actions upon ſo weak a Topick as that of <hi>Example,</hi> ſince we know that no Crime can be perpetrated, no Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation introduced, no Violation offer'd even to Heaven it ſelf, but will be all warrantable, if their being ſubſequent to a like practice of former Ages frees them from Guilt. Rebellion is as ancient as the Creation, it firſt divided the Court of Heaven, and deprived <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his Accomplices of their Glory, and then threw Man out of the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> and the ſtate of Innocence into a rough tract of the Earth, and yet rougher anguiſhes and perplexities of Sin. An obedience to God's Command to <hi>encreaſe and multiply</hi> was not long paid, when of the few Inhabitants of the World, one, and he the moſt harmleſs too, fell a Sacrifice to his Brothers envy and makers affection. Idolatry (the <hi>Jews</hi> only excepted) was the common Worſhip of Mankind, and whatever Species of Chriſtianity was firſt planted in this Iſland, 'tis certain that Popery not many Years ſince was the legal and known Religion univerſally embrac'd by the People; yet God forbid we ſhould now pretend Rebellion, Murder, Idolatry and Popery to be all lawful becauſe we find ancient times memorable for ſuch impicties. 'Tis no plea in Divinity to alledge the preſcription which ſin has gain'd upon us, as an excuſe.</p>
            <p>The alterations ſucceſſively made in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Commonwealth are nothing pertinent to the matter for whoſe proof they were brought, for they were either by a previous command or ſubſequent approbation of God manifeſted to his Prophets introduced and continued for their reſpective portions of time, and when we have ſuch viſible diſpenſations of the divine Will imparted to us, we will then be as active in our Obedience and Submiſſion to God as the Authors of ſuch Pamphlets are in their Malice and Diſloyalty to their King; but till then we hope no man will expect that, becauſe God who is the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100041:5"/> Author of all Governments, and knows the ways and methods that are moſt ſuitable to their happineſs, has often changed the form he preſcribed to the <hi>Jews;</hi> Therefore we Men, that are poſſeſſed with Intereſt, Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Ambition may do the like upon Motives no ways certain or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident.</p>
            <p>His Example of <hi>Don Sancho,</hi> who by the approbation of the three Eſtates took the Crown which was the right of his Nephews, is no leſs impertinent to his purpoſe, for he himſelf allows in the <hi>4th.</hi> page of his Pamphlet, that in <hi>Spain</hi> the next Heir cannot ſucceed but by the approbation of the Nobility, Biſhops and States of the Realm; If ſo, is not that Kingdom in a manner Elective? and what parity is there between it and ours, where the next Heir is actual King without the Ceremonies of Coronation, or the conſent, choice or agreement of any? He is yet more unfortunate in the Caſe of <hi>Hugo Capetus,</hi> who by the choice (as he ſays) of the States of <hi>France</hi> invaded the Throne, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> the next Heir; For whereas his Poſition was in the beginning, That any Government was alterable or ammendable by the mutual conſent of the <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Governed,</hi> he now very learnedly proves this, by ſaying that the States alone did exclude <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> which ſurely are not tho abſolute Governours, at leaſt without the lawful King at the head of 'em, in any Hereditary Government in the World: If they be, an actual Prince may be depos'd with as much Juſtice as an Heir can be excluded the Succeſſion, and ſo (for ought we know) his <hi>R. H.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once removed out of their way, the next attempt will be againſt His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>His Story of <hi>William Rufus</hi> and his Brother <hi>Henrie</hi>'s ſucceſſively enjoying the Crown is to as little purpoſe as his Foreign Examples; for as it is certain that neither of them had any right whilſt <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> was living, ſo their being admitted Kings by the conſent of the Realm (that is, I ſuppoſe, of a Parliament) gave them no Title at all, by this Gentleman's ſuppoſition, who ſays that in ſuch Caſes the Will of the Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned muſt concur. The ſame Anſwer ſerves to defeat the pretended Legality of all his other examples, and therefore I leave him to bemoan his Ignorance, or plead Drunkenneſs (for his Diſcourſe was delivered in a Tavern) as an excuſe of his impertinencies. And I hope none of us will be ſo Unchriſtian or Impolitick as to think, that becauſe by the Treaſons and Conſpiracies of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, diſloyal and deſigning Perſons, the Crown was now and then transferred from one Family to another we now muſt do the like, when the occaſions of ſuch innovations are perfectly taken away, not only by the conjunction of the White and Red Roſes, but likewiſe by the meeting of the Bloud Royal of the three Kingdoms in the Perſon of our preſent Monarch. To attempt this, were to bring all the evils upon the People to which the unſteddy courſe of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Affairs can poſſibly ſubject them; For where a gap is once opened to Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſnatchings one from another, the moſt bloudy Commotions imaginable ſucceed, in which neceſſity obliging the parties to the practice of promiſcuous Violences, Depredations and Slaughters, the People at laſt wearied with the Cruelties and Calamities of War, and to purchaſe quiet at any rate, often give up their Liberty to the Conquerour, and make the publick Deſolations of their Country its Grave; ſo terrible an Example of which we had in the late Troubles, that ſurely none, but ſuch as are Betrayers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty, or deſtined for Slavery, will venture the like Tranſgreſſion the ſecond time.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100041:5"/>
            <p> It will be ſaid, that his <hi>R. H.</hi> has embraced the Papal Religion, which will be as deſtructive to the Temporal and Eternal Well-fare of the whole Kingdom, in caſe he ſhould come to the Crown, as it is to his own Soul, and therefore, to prevent ſo univerſal a miſcheif, it is neceſſary his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſt ſhould be ſacrificed to the publick. To this I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. No man ever yet gave any particular convincing inſtance of his being a Papiſt, beſides his not conforming to the Religion now eſtabliſhed by Law, or not taking ſuch Oaths as would make him capable of enjoying all the great Offices of the Kingdom, to which his Birth and Merit without them might juſtly entitle him; But this Non-conformity is agreeable not only to all the Claſſes and Subdiviſions of Proteſtantiſm, but to all the other Forms and Modes of Worſhip in the World, and his unwillingneſs to ſwear, proceeds, for ought we know, rather from a belief that all Oaths are unlawful, as not only many of old Chriſtians, our preſent Quakers, but the moſt refined and ingeniouſly learn'd of all Modern Sects the Socinians, maintain, than that he thinks the matter of thoſe the Law now requires to be Damnable or Heretical, and therefore we may as well ſay that he is a <hi>Presbyterian, Independent,</hi> or <hi>Quaker,</hi> or <hi>Socinian;</hi> or, which is yet worſe, a <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Jew,</hi> as that he is a <hi>Papiſt:</hi> and to ſpeak Truth our too much curioſity, and ſtrict ſcrutiny into this matter, is far leſs warrantable than his concealing his opinion; for <hi>Who art thou that judgest another Man's Serva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth; yea he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of Darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the Counſels of the hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If he be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> now, who can tell but the powerful operations of the Holy Spirit may by changing his Sentiments concerning Sacred things remove thoſe jealouſles and fears with which we are now ſo ſtrongly poſſeſt, and add to his future happineſs the temporal bleſſings we ſo much dread to loſe? Faith is the Gift of God, and he being moſt juſt and merciful, will we hope beſtow it where it may have the kindeſt reception, and bring forth its Fruits in greateſt Plenty, that is on a Prince whoſe natural Endowments and moral Vertues are ſo eminent as, (if enliven'd by true Faith as we hope they are) to enable him when a King to conquer the Atheiſm, Irreligion, Debauchery and other ſwarms of Evils, with which the Age abounds, by his Example, as well as the Enemies of the Crown by his Valour; 'Tis our Duty then to wait the leiſure of Providence, and not by a raſh, not to ſay a wicked attempt, endeavour to deprive him of his right, and our ſelves of the happineſs his enjoying the Religion, as well as the Kingdom, of his Anceſtors, may poſſibly ſecure unto us; nor do I ſee any ſatisfactory reaſon, why he ſhould be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely uſed, allowing no hopes of his Converſion or Return to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for our Religion is ſufficiently guarded by ſeveral Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he can never repeal; And beſides, His preſent Majeſty is (thank God) Strong, Active, and Vigorous, and likely enough either to out-live his <hi>R. H.</hi> or leave him ſo old and crazy as to want briskneſs anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his zeal, to attempt any notable change or innovation in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Popery</hi> in the ſingle Perſon of the Prince, whatever is ſaid to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100041:6"/> is conſiſtent enough with the Welfare of the Subjects, though of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſwaſion, as appears in <hi>Germany,</hi> where in many Places the Body of the People are of the Reformed, and the Prince of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without diffidence or fear, or the narrow Spirit of Perſecution of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their ſide.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the Principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> no Prince can be depos'd, or forfeit his Right to the Sovereignty, purely upon the ſcore of Religion; and as long as that Church is in being, and the rule and management, next after the King, of all things as well Spiritual as Temporal, is by the Laws of the Land in its hands, and the hands of ſuch as are Members of it, and obedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Practice and Diſcipline of ſo pious and charitable a Mother, 'tis evident that none elſe can be proper Judges, or have cognizance of the point now in debate, but they; and therefore his <hi>R. H.</hi> appeals to them, and is not at all concern'd at what others can do, who doubtleſs have as great a deſire to dethrone the King as to bar the Succeſſion, could it be done with as much ſecurity and ſafety; For as he who intentionally and deliberately would deſtroy an Infant in the Mothers Womb, by cauſing an abortion, would never ſcruple the bringing of him to an untimely end after his coming into the World, did not the Law appoint Death for the Puniſhment of this, though not of the other. So he, that on the account of Religion, would exclude ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the poſſibility he has to a Crown, would make no conſcience of diſcharging an actual Prince, from his Royal Function, upon the ſame or other motives, were not his poſſeſſion fenced and guarded by the Law, which makes all ſuch attempts High-Treaſon, and ſo expoſes him to all the evils attending ſo great a Crime.</p>
            <p>But after all, why ſo much rancor, hatred and averſion againſt his <hi>R. H:</hi> who of all men living is the moſt paſſionate Lover of his Country, and under whom, if ever it ſhould be his lot to wear the Imperial Crown, it would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be as happy as under any that ſwayed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Scepter ſince the Conqueſt; having ſo many Princley Qualities, though now clouded and kept conceal'd from the eyes of the Nation, by the artifice of his Adverſaries, as would fill the hearts of all true <hi>Engliſh-</hi>men with Love and Reſpect, and thoſe of his Enemies, whether Domeſtick or Foreign, with Fear and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; For he is a Prince of a Noble Preſence and affable Behaviour, with a mixture of pleaſantneſs in his Words and Actions, that wins powerfully the affections of all that approach him. His diſcourſes are always pertinent and ſolid, free from Flouriſhes and a vain and empty Oſtentation of Wit, which ſorts better with the levity of mimical Heroes, upon a Theatre, then the true Grandeur of real Princes in a Court.</p>
            <p>He is of a moſt high Spirit, and invincible Courage, of mature Wiſdom, and ſingular Induſtry and Application to buſineſs, wary in Council and quick in Execution; He hates above all things a perpetual fluctuation and unſteddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Meaſures and Politicks of Government, becauſe it makes it a Riddle to it ſelf as vvell as to all other Nations, and forces it to wander and ſtray from the propoſed Ends, having no clue of reaſon to guide it through ſo many Labyrinths of Confuſions, and therefore is conſtant and inflexible in his Reſolutions, whilſt ſuitable to she true Intereſt of the Nation, which often created him great and dangerous Enemies, every one hoping in the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and variety of Councils to be able to get the Miniſtry into his own hands, and therefore looking upon him with an Eye of Envy, as the hinderance and main obſtacle of their ambitious purpoſes.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100041:6"/>
            <p> He is true and firm to his Friends and Servants, whom not chance or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but parts and merit, with a long and unſtain'd reputation of Honeſty, places in his Favour; and as his love is not to the Perſons, but their Vertues, ſo his hatred extends only to their Vices, and ends as ſoon as they begin to give any viſible ſigns of their Repentance; and whatever is ſaid to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary by ſome of his Enemies, who would ſcare the reſt, and harden them in their wickedneſs, by putting them into a deſpair of forgiveneſs, he is not of a vindicative Spirit, for none ever yet fell otherwiſe then gently by his means, or ſmarted any longer under his indignation, then they continued obſtinate and wilful in the purſuit of his and the Countries diſquiet, as might be proved by a thouſand inſtances too tedious to be here recounted. In ſhort, he is of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and Souldierly Temper, patient of cold, heat, hunger, thirſt and all the toyls and fatigues naturally incident to War either by Sea or Land; his Valour is ſprightly, but not raſh; his Conduct wary and ſecure, and the events of his Battels and Engagements ſtill Fortunate and Succesful, all which would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation (for whoſe Genius Providence has fitted him) readier to ſhed their Bloud to acquire him new Crowns, then deprive him of thoſe Nature has already entitled him to, after the Death of his Brother, had not the inveterate malice of ſome reſtleſs and Factious Spirits poſſeſs'd them with an opinion of his having deſigned for ſo many years to involve them in Bloud and Slaughter; the falſhood of which will eaſily appear, to any that conſider his actions all along ſince his and the King's Return from their Exile, to which ſuch Practices as are now a foot drove them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. AS it is doubtful whether he renounced the Religion, wherein he was Educated, and embraced <hi>Popery</hi> more then <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> or any other form of Chriſtianity diſtinct from the National Worſhip; ſo it is certain, that he always adhered to the True Intereſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> I mean the Glory and Preſervation of the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which His Royal Father conſigned to his Poſterity, Sealed with his Blood, ſhed by Men out-doing in Practice (though not in Principles) the <hi>Modern Reformers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. He hath made it his Buſineſs to free his Majeſties Subjects from their Fatal Longings after a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> to which the Contagion of the late Times had Enſlaved them; And by his Addreſſes, Sollicitations, and Preferments, with which he was able (when in Power) to Reward ſuch brave Souls as ſignaliz'd their Loyalty to his Father or Brother in the Diſorder of their Affairs; He hath brought that Virtue in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion again, and made more Converts to the Royal Authority, than all the Orthodox Clergy with their Preachings and Arguments, (how Learnedly and Induſtriouſly ſoever handled,) were able to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quis enim Virtutem amplectitur ipſam, Praemia ſi tollas?</hi>—The Truth of this will appear eaſily to any, that will take the trouble to conſider, how notably the Reverence due to Majeſty is impair'd, and how Univerſally the <hi>Anti-monarchical Principles</hi> are ſpread with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe Seven or Eight Years, ſince upon the miſconceiv'd Jealouſies of the People, He declin'd the Influence He had upon the State, by his Great Imployments.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100041:7"/> III. Through the Power, which his Fidelity and Ability gave him over the King, He hath procured the chiefeſt Places of Strength in the Nation; And moſt of the great Truſts, as well Civil and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as Military, to be confer'd upon known Royaliſts, and ſworn Enemies to ſuch, as under the ſpecious pretence of ſecuring our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, would again involve Us in the ſame Calamities, from which, Providence hath ſo lately Deliver'd Us.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. He hath been by his Advice and Influence over the great Miniſters the Principal Oppoſer of all the <hi>French Agents,</hi> who in ſubſervience to Their Intereſt, were often tampering for promoting of an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government,</hi> and of making the Kings Intereſt both diſtinct from, and oppoſite to that of his People: And this He hath done in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the <hi>Fundamental Laws,</hi> for which he always teſtifyed a great Veneration, and to prevent the ill Effects conſtantly attending ſuch Pernicious Councels: For He well knew from the Hiſtory of ſome of his Progenitors, that an Attempt to remove the <hi>Antient Bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Land-marks of Government, never miſſes opening a way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Confuſion; Of which, Ambitious Men taking Advantage, by their wheedling Practices, often perſwade the</hi> People <hi>that are Heady, Valiant, and Jealous of their Liberty, to run into Rebellion; which as it generally terminates in the Ruine of the</hi> Prince, <hi>or</hi> Subject, <hi>ſo it often Enſlaves both to the Power of a</hi> Foreign Enemy; <hi>For which Reaſon He always held the Conſtitution of the Kingdom as Sacred and Inviolable, in reference to the People, as He now does in regard of his own Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. It was This <hi>Active and Vigilant Prince,</hi> that (poſſeſs'd with Flames of Love towards the City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> as violent as thoſe that reduc'd it to Aſhes,) expoſed his Perſon to a Thouſand Dangers, to Reſcue it from Deſtruction. He bufied thoſe Hands (deſtin'd for <hi>Managing of Scepters)</hi> in Breaking open Pipes and Conduits for Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, reach'd Buckets as nimbly as any of the Common People; clear'd the Streets from the Throngs and Crouds, that hindred the carrying away of their Goods, Appointed his <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> to Conduct them to ſecure places: And in fine, for ſeveral Nights and Days, (without Sleep, or reſt from Labour,) was ſeen in all parts, giving the neceſſary Orders for preventing the further ſpreading of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration, as if Love (which uſually works Miracles,) had Multiply'd him, or rather given him a kind of Ubiquity. And this He did, partly to ſhew his Gratitude to his Beloved <hi>Londoners,</hi> whoſe Minion He was, but chiefly to ſave the <hi>Magazine</hi> of the Strength and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Kingdom from Deſolation and Ruine.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100041:7"/> VI. Whatever is ſaid of his Inclination to <hi>Popery,</hi> or the Humour of the <hi>French Nation,</hi> 'tis Evident, He underſtands, and purſues the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>England</hi> ſo well, that to check the Torrent of their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, by creating them work at home, he forwarded (as much as poſſibly he could) an Alliance, which <hi>Monſieur Rohux,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman propos'd to His Majeſty for the Securing of <hi>Foreign Proteſtants;</hi> And it had in all probability come to a very happy Iſſue, had not <hi>Monſieur Rovigny Leiger,</hi> Embaſſador from <hi>France</hi> at this Court, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it, by corrupting one <hi>Monſieur de Verax,</hi> That after the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in the <hi>Vivarets,</hi> fled hither, and rid ſome time in the Guards; who (through Neceſſity, or Frailty,) made Sale of the whole Secret, (and with It, of the Safety of his Friend, and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in <hi>France,)</hi> for Two Hundred <hi>Piſtols.</hi> Upon notice of which Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, <hi>Monſieur Rohux</hi> retired into <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where being Seiz'd by a Party of <hi>French Horſe,</hi> he was convey'd to the <hi>Bastile;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome times Impriſonment, broken upon the Wheel at the place of Execution.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. It was againſt his Will that the firſt and laſt <hi>Dutch</hi> Wars were commenced, yet the reſolution being taken, by thoſe, whoſe Will is a Law, in ſheathing, or unſheathing the Sword of the Subjects, he valiantly, and for the Glory of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, in the <hi>Firſt,</hi> with many Thouſands of their Souldiers and Seamen, ſunk a great part of their Fleet, blew up their Admiral, and with him the very Reputation of their Naval Power, thought before Invincible, and by Sacking of <hi>Scheveling</hi> made proud <hi>Amsterdam</hi> tremble, for which great Services, as <hi>England</hi> ſhall ever be indebted, ſo the Parliament, then ſitting, was pleas'd to vote him 100000 <hi>l.</hi> as a ſmall acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Merit, and their Affections; and <hi>London,</hi> and all other Places, entertain'd him with Acclamations of Joy. Thus you ſee the viciſſitude of Humane Affairs, and how Fortune, which then ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Hearts and Cities of the Kingdom, for his Reception, now ſhuts them, and all the Avenues to the Crown againſt him, which may ſerve as an Example to <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> who never did any thing to recommend him, beſides the effect of Chance, his being a Protſtant, how little reaſon he has to rely upon the Affections of a Multitude, that ſo eaſily forgets the real worth of their Darling Prince.—Nor did he leſs deſerve the hatred of his Enemy, and love of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in the laſt War, in which, though with the many notable Diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of the Wind and Tyde, being at Anchor when ſet upon, and the ſucceeding Miſt, he yet behav'd himſelf with that Gallantry, as made <hi>De Ruiter</hi> own us to be Invincible, and more than men, and particularly, that His <hi>R. H.</hi> exceeded all the Admirals in <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> as much by his Bravery, as he did by his Birth. having, in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100041:8"/> the heat of the Engagement, (when Re-fitting, would loſe the Benefit of his Orders, and Action,) changed Ships oftener than Great Generals at Land, have done their Horſes.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. It was this Zealous Prince, for the Honour and Safety (of <hi>England,</hi> that adviſed the forming of the <hi>Triple League,</hi> which was the wiſeſt Conjunction, and moſt for the Glory of the King's Reign, and the Preſervation of His Dominions, that ever he entred into. And this he did, not only to curb <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Power he ſaw was already over-grown, but to ſave all the weaker Parts of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> from the Attempts of the ſtronger; For he knew that while that <hi>League</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued firm, the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> would have conſtrued all Deſigns upon us in <hi>England.</hi> as done againſt thoſe of the ſame Intereſt with themſelves, and in favour of whoſe Security, they had entred into that <hi>Alliance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. He was ſo great a <hi>Stranger</hi> to the breaking of the <hi>Triple League,</hi> and ſeizing the <hi>Dutch Smyrna</hi> Fleet, that Sir <hi>Edward Sprag,</hi> who was known to be his Creature, was not thought fit to be entruſted with the Secret, which occaſion'd the <hi>Miſcarriage</hi> of the Deſign, and the Eternal Glory of his Highneſs.</p>
            <p n="10">X. He hath not only mantained Correſpondence with Foreign Princes, by His Majeſties <hi>approbation,</hi> for ſecuring the well-fare of the Nation, but likewiſe endeavour'd to draw them into an <hi>Alliance</hi> with us, to oppoſe the <hi>French</hi> particularly, or any other Foreign Enemy, that by Counſel, or Action, would endeavour the overthrow of our <hi>Legal Government.</hi> And beſides many evidences of this, which are needleſs to mention at preſent, the ſecret Counſel, which, by His Majeſties Conſent, he gave to our ſeveral <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> abroad, and are yet to be ſeen, together with the many Letters he wrote to the ſame purpoſe, do uncontrollably demonſtrate it.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. It was He, that when the late Expedition into <hi>Flanders,</hi> was thought really Deſigned againſt the <hi>French,</hi> put all his Equipage into a readineſs, and vow'd to retrieve the Reputation of <hi>England,</hi> by Death, or Conqueſt. But a <hi>Great Man,</hi> then at the Helm, (now for his many Villanies confin'd to the Hold,) thought fit by his <hi>Advice</hi> to make a <hi>Mock-General,</hi> for a <hi>Mock-Army,</hi> not daring to put ſuch a great Indignity upon any, that had Senſe to underſtand, or Courage to revenge it, which occaſion'd that Impoſition of Peace, under which all the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Christendom</hi> do, more or leſs, feel the heavy preſſures
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100041:8"/> of the <hi>French</hi> Inſolence, whereas, had not that Mercenary Lord put a ſtop to the Parliaments Proceedings, and the Duke's Reſolutions, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> had in a few years been reſtored to its Tranquility.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. He was ſo far from conſenting to, or co-operating in any part of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> that <hi>Oats</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> (the two Poles on which the whole Frame of it has its motion and circumgyration) did ſolemnly clear him, as appears by their ſeveral <hi>Depoſitions,</hi> and the <hi>Journals</hi> of both Houſes of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">XIII. It was the <hi>Duke,</hi> who, when Father <hi>Bedingfield</hi> brought him the <hi>Treaſonable Letters</hi> concerning the <hi>PLOT,</hi> immediately ſhew'd them to the King, that ſo the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> and their <hi>Papers</hi> might be ſeiz'd, and the Truth ſifted to the Bottom.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. It is he, who this Summer, at <hi>Windſor,</hi> facilitated the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Alliance,</hi> made between This and The Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Security of both Nations, againſt all Enemies whatſoever, and to the unſpeakable Advantage of our Merchants in that Country, and all other parts of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. The incredible Expences of the Crown having drain'd His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties <hi>Exchequer,</hi> to that degree, that he wanted Money for defraying the <hi>Vaſt Charges,</hi> of <hi>Maintaining</hi> and <hi>Defending Tangier,</hi> his <hi>R. H.</hi> rather then ſo Imporrant a Place, for the Trade of the <hi>Streights,</hi> ſhould fall into the hands of the <hi>Moors,</hi> and, perhaps, by them be deliver'd up to worſe Enemies, generouſly disburs'd a very conſiderable Sum of Money, for its Preſervation; and by that Action ſhewed how ſollicitous he is about the Well-fare of <hi>England,</hi> even at the very time, when it contrives his Deſtruction, which is an infallible Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his being in his Nature and Principles very averſe from Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity and Revenge. To which his Enemies have reported him ſo addicted, that in the opinion of many, he is accounted irreconcilable; whereas he is ſo much of a contrary temper, that as he equals <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Greatneſs of Mind, and firmneſs of Reſolution; ſo he out-does him in the particular Character of <hi>Remembring all things but Injuries.</hi> Chriſtianity has made him ſo unalterable in this Point; that as Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Examples do manifeſt his Sincerity in it, ſo his common and conſtant ſaying, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>as he never forgets good turns, ſo he can eaſily forgive bad ones,</hi> is an invincible proof of his Inclination. He needs no <hi>Cicero</hi> to plead the Cauſe of the Guilty, or heap upon him extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Praiſes for his Mercy to his Enemies in Diſtreſs; His own
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100041:9"/> 
               <hi>Genius</hi> leads him to the practice of that Gallantry, without the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or Flattery of others. <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> was not with more readineſs and affection received into <hi>Caeſars</hi> Favours, than all Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries may be into his, upon quitting thoſe Crimes, for which he is now Vogu'd inexorable; And, were it his Fortune to have the full knowledge of this particular Virtue ſpread as far as the Effects have reach'd, I am confident it would be impoſſible for the Malice of a few, to impoſe upon others, ſo, as to make them continue their violent Actions againſt him, and think that their Security, (which is really their Hazard) inſtead of Repenting, to go on to greater Ills upon ſo groundleſs and malicious a ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as he believes that none deſerves to have Obedience paid to him, when a King, that is Unruly and Refractory to his Princes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand when a Subject, ſo he is ſubmiſſive to His Majeſties Pleaſure, even beyond the Preſcript of Law, having now the third time, with the manifeſt hazard of his Perſon, beſides the difficulties and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of travelling, quitted his Native Country, upon the firſt notice of his Commands.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what a Prince <hi>England</hi> is weary of, and that as a weak and diſeas'd Stomack, nauſeates even the beſt Reſtorative, ſo our Nation in the Confuſions and Diſtractions the fear of loſing its Liberty has put it into, dreads none ſo much as him, who of all men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, if a King, would be the moſt able and willing to Defend them. But I hope <hi>Scotland</hi> underſtands his Merit, and its own Intereſt better, and will ſecure him that Ancient Throne, whoſe Splendor is much abated, ſince that Kingdom is, by the Abſence of their Kings, in a manner become a Province; if he fills it once with an excluſion from ours, it will ſoon regain its firſt Luſtre, and your name will be as glorious, as ours will be deteſtable to Poſterity: But however, as I would not have the happy Union of the two Kingdoms diſſolv'd, ſo I hope that either our Repentance will recal him, or that, <hi>Alexander</hi> like, his own victorious Sword, will in time cut this Gordian Knot of the Succeſſion, and Eſtabliſh him in his Right: To which, as I doubt not but you will be aſſiſting, ſo you need not queſtion the help of all Loyal men here, and particularly of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 3. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant B. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
